Congregational Christian Historical Society records, 1899-2010.
Congregational Library Archives
Congregational Christian Historical Society records, 1899-2010.
RG1187
Congregational Library Archives
3.49 Cubic Feet
(4 boxes)
The Congregational Christian Historical Society was formed to help preserve and make accessible the historical records of Congregationalists, Congregational Societies, and related monuments and historical sites. Frederick L. Fagley was the first executive secretary; following his death the Congregational Christian Historical Society moved to the Congregational House, located at 14 Beacon Street in Boston. By 2010 the organization had formally disbanded; its collections and mission are now held by the Congregational Library Archives. This collection includes photographs, printed material, Minutes and Committee Reports, Individual Correspondences and Files, CCHS Founding Documents, Celebrations and Anniversaries, Histories and Church Projects and financial information.
Congregational Christian Historical Society
Fagley, Frederick Louis, 1879-1958
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Collection has been housed at the Congregational Library and Archives for sometime, first year it was received is unknown; Accession: 2014-37.
Historical Information
The Congregational Christian Historical Society was formed for multiple reasons, as noted in the original articles of incorporation. They included cultivating a deeper interest in the history of the Congregational Christian Churches in all aspects, to encourage and to participate in the creation, preservation and correlation of records, the scholarly use of historical materials and the production of historical works, to promote the observance of anniversaries and other occasions of historical interest, and the preservation of monuments and historical sites, and finally, to work in cooperation with the relevant instrumentalities of the United Church of Christ, the National Association of Congregational Christian Churches, the Conservative Congregational Christian Conference, the Evangelical and Reformed Historical Society, among other similar organizations. Frederick L. Fagley, the Society's first executive secretary, led the group while it was housed in New York, but following his death they moved to the Congregational House, located at 14 Beacon Street in Boston. By 2010, the organization had formally disbanded and its material and mission are now carried on by the Congregational Library and Archives.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes photographs, printed material, Minutes and Committee Reports, Individual Correspondences and Files, CCHS Founding Documents, Celebrations and Anniversaries, Histories and Church Projects and financial information.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically except for the Individual Correspondences and Files sub-series, which is arranged alphabetically.
Series 1: Photography and Printed Media, 1899-2005.
Series 2: Society Records, 1941-2009.
Subseries 1: Celebrations and Anniversaries, 1941-2005.
Subseries 2: CCHS Founding Documents, 1949-2009.
Subseries 3: Minutes and Committee Reports, 1951-2007.
Subseries 4: History, 1952-2000.
Subseries 5: Individual Correspondences and Files, 1953-2007.
Subseries 6: Church Projects, 1955-2004.
Series 3: Financial Information, 1949-2010.
Associations, institutions, etc.; Correspondence.; Church finance.; Corporate minutes.; Congregational Christian Historical Society; Fagley, Frederick Louis, 1879-1958
- Photography and printed media, 1899 2005; 1899-2005; 23 Items; (2 volumes, 21 folders)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains photographs and printed material related to the Congregational Christian Historical Society.
  - Printed media, 1899 2005; 1899-2005; 8 Items; (2 volumes, 6 folders)
    This sub-series contains printed material created or owned by the Congreagational Christian Historical Society, including newsletters, newspaper articles and postcards.
    - News articles, 1899 2005; 1899, 1983-2005 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Newsletters, 1954 1958; 1954-1958 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    - Newsletters, 1959 1964; 1959-1964 (Box 2, Volume 2)
    - Postcards, 1962 1963; 1962-1963, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Newsletters, 1962 1968; 1962-1968 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Newsletters, 1969 1982; 1969-1982 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Newsletters, 1982 1994; 1982-1994 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Newsletters, 1995 2004; 1995-2004 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Photos, 1907 2002; 1907-2002; 15 Folders
    This sub-series contains photographs of annual meetings and other church events.
    - Church pictures of various officials, 1907 1963; 1907-1963 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Photographs, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Photographs, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Photographs, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Photographs, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Photographs, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Photographs, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - CCHS annual meeting, May 4-5th, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Hebron marker, May 8-9, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Annual meeting, May 11-12, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Photographs, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Washington gladden plaque, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Pilgimage to Henry Obookiah's Cornwall grave, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Newton historical exhibit, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - New England monuments, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Society records, 1941 2009; 1941-2009; 117 Folders
  This series contains various society records, including Minutes and Committee Reports, Individual Correspondences and Files, CCHS Founding Documents, Celebrations and Anniversaries, Histories and Church Projects.
  - Celebrations and anniversaries, 1941 2005; 1941-2005; 13 Folders
    This sub-series contains information on anniversaries and celebrations. Includes the 10th and 25th Anniversary, Cambridge Synod Celebration and anniversary surveys.
    - Cambridge Synod celebration, 1941 1946; 1941-1946 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Cambridge Synod celebration, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Writing church histories and anniversary, 1948 1982; 1948-1982 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Cambridge Synod celebration, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - A Significant Anniversary by Fred Field Goodsell, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - 10th anniversary of CCHS, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Church music and anniversaries, 1971 1992; 1971-1992 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - 25th anniversary of CCHS, May 10, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - UCC 25th anniversary, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Church anniversary and fashion, 1991 1992; 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Vermont conference bi-centennial, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Anniversary surveys, 1997 2005; 1997-2005 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Cambridge platform anniversary, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - CCHS founding documents, 1949 2009; 1949-2009; 10 Folders
    This sub-series contains documents related to the founding of the Congregational Christian Historical Society, including constitiutions, by-laws, acts of incorporation and information on the eventual dissolution.
    - Founding documents, 1949 1951; 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Founding documents, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 42-43)
    - Founding documents, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Constitution, 1952 1959; 1952-1959 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Founding documents, 1953 1959; 1953-1959 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Act of incorporation, May 27, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - By-Laws and incorporation, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - By-Laws and incorporation, 1978 2004; 1978, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Dissolution of CCHS, 2004 2009; 2004-2009 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Minutes and committee reports, 1951 2007; 1951-2007; 44 Folders
    This collection contains meeting minutes, board of director's minutes and executive committee minutes from the Congregational Christian Historical Society.
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 1953 1954; 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 1955 1956; 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 1957 1958; 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 1959 1960; 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 1961 1965; 1961-1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 1966 1967; 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 1968 1970; 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 1969 1974; 1969-1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 1975 1976; 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 1977 1978; 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 1982 1983; 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 1984 1985; 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 1986 1987; 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 1988 1989; 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 1990 1991; 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 1992 1993; 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 1994 1995; 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 1996 1997; 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Nomination committee, 1997 2005; 1997-2005 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 1998 1999; 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 2000 2001; 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Planning for spring meeting, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 2002 2003; 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 2004 2006; 2004-2006 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, May 11, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
    - Board of director's meeting minutes, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Meeting minutes and reports, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
    - Executive committee minutes, 1951 1952; 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Executive committee minutes, 1961 1963; 1961-1963 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Executive committee minutes, 1964 1965; 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Executive committee minutes, 1966 1970; 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Executive committee minutes, 1971 1972; 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Executive committee minutes, 1973 1975; 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Executive committee minutes, 1976 1977; 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - History, 1952 2000; 1952-2000; 11 Folders
    This sub-series contains information on the history of various groups affiliated with Congregational Christian Historical Society, including the ACA, UCC Historical Commission, UCC Women's History and the Evangelical and Reformed Historical Society.
    - Information on Christian Churches, 1952 1965; 1952-1965 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - ACA and CCHS history, 1956 2000; 1956-2000 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Evangelical and Reformed Historical Society history, 1958 1997; 1958-1997 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Handouts and information, 1958 2006; 1958-1977, 2004-2006 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - UCC Historical Commission, 1964 1975; 1964-1975 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - History, 1964 2000; 1964-1984, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Historical Commission, 1975 1998; 1975, 1992-1998 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Lifetime members, 1987 1990; 1987-1990 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - UCC women's history, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Outreach and handouts, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Set of quotes, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Individual correspondences and files, 1953 2007; 1953-2007; 22 Folders
    This collection contains files and correspondeces for various members of the Congregational Christian Historical Society.
    Arrangement
    This sub-series is arranged alphabetically.
    - Atkins, Gaius Glenn, 1953 1956; 1953-1956 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Deems, Mervin M., 1971 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Edwards, Robert L., 1995 1997; 1995-1997 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - English, James F., 1953 1977; 1953, 1961-1977 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Fagley, Frederick L., 1948 1956; 1948-1956 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Fagley correspondence, 1956 1957; 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Fagley, Frederick L., 1957 1960; 1957-1960 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Fagley, Frederick L., 1961 1972; 1961-1972 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Guptill, Nathanael M., 1990 2007; 1990-1997, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Haddix, James L., 1984 1991; 1984-1991 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Haddix, James L., 1992 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Haddix, James L., 1993 1999; 1993-1999 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Hambrick-Stowe, Charles, 2000 2001; 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Horton, Gordon, 1954 1966; 1954-1966 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Knight, Dennis R., 1988 2001; 1988-2001 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Merrill, Charles, 1942 1961; 1942-1961 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Taylor, Richard H., 1972 1975; 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Taylor, Richard H., 1976 1990; 1976-1990 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Taylor, Richard H., 1991 1996; 1991-1996 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Wilson, Arthur E. memorial, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Worthley, Harold Field, 1960 1976; 1960-1976 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Correpondence and notes, 1969 2000; 1969-2000 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Church projects, 1955 2004; 1955-2004; 17 Folders
    This sub-series contains information related to the various projects done by the Congregational Christian Historical Society, including the Mayflower project, Scrooby Manor Project, Essay Contest, Frederick L. Fagley Award, event schedules and more.
    - CCHS merger, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Mayflower project, 1955 1957; 1955-1957 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Scrooby historical marker, 1955 1959; 1955-1959 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Vaughan Danby memorial, 1964 1973; 1964, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Boston landmarks calendar, 1969-09 1970-11; September 1969-November 1970 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Pilgrim Father's Information Center, 1979 1980; 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Little Baddow project, 1983 1987; 1983-1987 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Event schedules, 1983 2004; 1983-2004 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Video projects, 1987 1998; 1987-1998 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Suitcase seminars, 1990 2000; 1990, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Speaker's Bureau, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Frederick L. Fagley Award, 1992 2004; 1992-2004 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Scrooby Manor project, 1993 1995; 1993-1995 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Bookmarks project, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Essay contest project, 1994 2001; 1994-2001 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Historical markers project, 1996 1997; 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Fulton County of New York, undated (Box 3, Folder 57)
- Financial information, 1949 2010; 1949-2010; 4 Folders
  This series contains financial information related to the Congregational Christian Historical Society.
  - Annuity fund, 1949 1955; 1949-1955 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - United Church Foundation fund, 1979 1998; 1979-1998 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - United Church Foundation fund, 2003 2006; 2003-2006 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Form 990, 2009 2010; 2009-2010 (Box 3, Folder 61)